---
# empty front matter to force jekyll processing
---
<page
    action-0="history:set-year"
    action-0-argument-0="1865"
    action-1="player:set-mode"
    action-1-argument-0="overview"
    action-2="player:teleport"
    action-2-argument-0="82.0084"
    action-2-argument-1="30.89582"
    action-2-argument-2="252.7299"
    action-2-argument-3="0.2526493"
    action-2-argument-4="0.27566"
    action-2-argument-5="0.2570136"
>
	<button
        title="Previous"
        description="Incarceration and Exile"
        action-0="menu:previous-page"
    />

	<!-- <subtitle>3/4</subtitle> -->
    
    <title>Sakpedan, Wakanozanzan, and ongoing Dakhota Persecution</title>

    <body>
        Construction of this prison commenced in late 1864, when the fort commander wrote to the War Department that he
        had concerns about housing violent criminals with those who were imprisoned for petty offenses in the guardhouse.
        It is likely that he was engaging in racial profiling with this argument. Two of the earliest occupants of this
        prison were Sakpedan and Wakanozanzan, known in the media as Shakopee and Medicine Bottle. These men had fled to
        Canada at the end of the US-Dakota War in 1862, probably guessing that there would be no justice for them here in
        their homeland.
    </body>

    <body>
        If this was so, they were correct. US military men had drugged them and transported them to Fort Snelling where
        they stood accused of war crimes. But as members of a sovereign nation (recognized by a treaty with the US), did
        the military have the right to try them?
    </body>

    <image
        src="/assets/tour-prison/chief-shakopee-III.jpg"
        title="Sakpedan"
    />

    <image
        src="/assets/tour-prison/wakan-ozanzan.jpg"
        title="Wakanozanzan"
    />

    <image
        src="/assets/tour-prison/building-14-plan.jpg"
        title="Prison Floor Plan"
    />

    <body>
        Local newspapers depicted Sakpedan and Wakanozanzan in ugly, racially stereotyped terms. This was especially evident compared to
        their depiction of another prisoner, John Pryor, an enlisted Irish immigrant incarcerated for killing one of his fellow soldiers.
        All three men were sentenced to be executed. The Saint Paul Pioneer described Pryor as in a pitiable state, and that his crime was
        the result of inflamed passions and alcohol. In the same issue, Sakpedan and Wakanozanzan were described as being resigned to their
        fate, and murderers. Concerned citizens circulated petitions to commute the execution sentences of all three men, but only Pryor was
        successful. On November 11th, 1865, Sakpedan and Wakanozanzan were executed within sight of this prison.
    </body>

    <body>
        How do we remember Sakpedan and Wakanozanzan? Their descendants see them as men who fought to protect their families and communities,
        and are devastated that the public record depicts them as criminals. Read these examples from historic newspapers, and consider how
        racialized stereotypes are circulated and reproduced in the media today.
    </body>

    <image
        src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-8-executions-set.png"
        title="Executions Set"
    />

    <image
        src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-11-executions-postponed.png"
        title="Executions Postponed"
    />

    <gallery
        src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-14-defense-letter-page1.png"
        title="A Letter in Defense of the Prisoners"
    >
        <gallery-image
            src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-14-defense-letter-page1.png"
        />
        <gallery-image
            src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-14-defense-letter-page2.png"
        />
        <gallery-image
            src="/assets/tour-prison/1865-10-14-defense-letter-page3.png"
        />
    </gallery>
    

    <button
        title="Next"
        description="Dakhota Omniciye – Truth-telling Today"
        action-0="menu:next-page"
        action-0-argument-0="tour-dakota-war-3"
    />
</page>